<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><NDELTA xmlns="JNdiff.org" collapse="true" commentnode="true" emptynode="true" ltrim="true" rtrim="true"><DELETE nn="407" nodecount="2"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1-remotesensing-10-00641" xmlns="">1</xref></DELETE><DELETE nn="409" nodecount="1">,</DELETE><DELETE nn="410" nodecount="2"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2-remotesensing-10-00641" xmlns="">2</xref></DELETE><DELETE nn="412" nodecount="1">,</DELETE><DELETE nn="413" nodecount="2"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3-remotesensing-10-00641" xmlns="">3</xref></DELETE><DELETE nn="415" nodecount="1">], the temporal resolution and availability of current very high spatial resolution satellite sensors (less than 10 m) are generally not sufficient nor flexible enough for many quantitative remote sensing applications, and they are thus of limited use in detecting and monitoring the dynamics of surficial environmental processes. Recent advances in Earth observation (i.e., EO) are opening new opportunities for environmental monitoring at finer scales [</DELETE><DELETE nn="416" nodecount="2"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4-remotesensing-10-00641" xmlns="">4</xref></DELETE><DELETE nn="418" nodecount="1">]. For instance, CubeSat platforms represent a promising satellite technology, operating predominantly in the visible to near-infrared portion of the electromagnetic spectrum, and provide high spatial and temporal resolution [</DELETE><DELETE nn="419" nodecount="2"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5-remotesensing-10-00641" xmlns="">5</xref></DELETE><DELETE nn="421" nodecount="1">]. Nevertheless, most of these satellites are operated by commercial organizations; hence, if short revisit times are required (i.e., for high-frequency monitoring), the cost of image acquisition can become a limiting factor. While manned airborne platforms can, in principle, provide both high spatial resolution and rapid revisit times, in practice, their use is routinely limited by operational complexity, safety, logistics, and cost. Their use becomes feasible only over medium-sized areas and remains largely within the domain of commercial operators. Recent advances in Unmanned Aerial Systems (UAS) technology have created an alternative monitoring platform that provides an opportunity to capture the spatial, spectral, and temporal requirements across a range of applications with relatively small investment. They offer high versatility, adaptability, and flexibility compared with manned airborne systems or satellites, and have the potential to be rapidly and repeatedly deployed for high spatial and temporal resolution data [</DELETE><DELETE nn="422" nodecount="2"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6-remotesensing-10-00641" xmlns="">6</xref></DELETE><DELETE nn="424" nodecount="1">].</DELETE><DELETE nn="425" nodecount="5"><p xmlns="">While UAS systems cannot compete with satellite imagery in terms of spatial coverage, they provide unprecedented spatial and temporal resolutions unmatched by satellite alternatives. Furthermore, they do so at a fraction of the satellite acquisition cost if the area of interest has relatively small extent. For example, a newly tasked high-resolution natural color image (50 cm/pixel) from a satellite (e.g., GeoEye-1) can cost up to 3000 USD. On the other hand, the initial outlay to acquire a single UAS with a natural color camera can be less than 1000 USD (see<xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-remotesensing-10-00641">Appendix A</xref>), with this delivering a dataset of high spatial resolution (several cm/pixel). Of course, the additional benefit of the UAS platform is that the temporal resolution is limited only by the number of flights (and power supply/battery capacity), so any cost equivalence is quickly overcome due to repeatability. The costs for acquiring UAS imagery are usually derived from the initial investment, the processing software, data storage, and associated (and ongoing) fieldwork expenses. However, after the initial investment, datasets can be delivered more often and at a higher resolution than by any other EO system.</p></DELETE><DELETE nn="431" nodecount="1">Matese et al. [</DELETE><DELETE nn="432" nodecount="2"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7-remotesensing-10-00641" xmlns="">7</xref></DELETE><DEL length="1" nn="408" pos="0">]</DEL><DEL length="156" nn="408" pos="413"> of a UAS-derived Normalized Difference Vegetation Index (NDVI) map over a 5 ha field is equal to 400 €/ha, while satellite products may cost about 30% more</DEL><INS length="13" nn="408" pos="0">Matese et al.</INS><DEL length="1" nn="406" pos="92">[</DEL><INS length="1" nn="406" pos="91">.</INS><INS length="85" nn="406" pos="93">While UAS systems cannot compete with satellite imagery in terms of spatial coverage.</INS></NDELTA>