<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><delta><insert digester="fnv" path="/3/1/3/13" radius="4" shortened="true"><fingerprint>5039bbd1;858f8603;1310d194;027a9443;44679145;b6849fa8;662e3aec;9e1e725e;c7c66c3d</fingerprint><newvalue><xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-remotesensing-10-00641">Appendix A</xref>), with this delivering a dataset of high spatial resolution (several cm/pixel). Of course, the additional benefit of the UAS platform is that the temporal resolution is limited only by the number of flights (and power supply/battery capacity), so any cost equivalence is quickly overcome due to repeatability. The costs for acquiring UAS imagery are usually derived from the initial investment, the processing software, data storage, and associated (and ongoing) fieldwork expenses. However, after the initial investment, datasets can be delivered more often and at a higher resolution than by any other EO system.</newvalue></insert><delete digester="fnv" path="/3/1/4" radius="4" shortened="true"><fingerprint>5039bbd1;858f8603;1310d194;027a9443;504c8365;b6849fa8;662e3aec;80b00970;11181e70</fingerprint><oldvalue>
      <p>While UAS systems cannot compete with satellite imagery in terms of spatial coverage, they provide unprecedented spatial and temporal resolutions unmatched by satellite alternatives. Furthermore, they do so at a fraction of the satellite acquisition cost if the area of interest has relatively small extent. For example, a newly tasked high-resolution natural color image (50 cm/pixel) from a satellite (e.g., GeoEye-1) can cost up to 3000 USD. On the other hand, the initial outlay to acquire a single UAS with a natural color camera can be less than 1000 USD (see <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-remotesensing-10-00641">Appendix A</xref>), with this delivering a dataset of high spatial resolution (several cm/pixel). Of course, the additional benefit of the UAS platform is that the temporal resolution is limited only by the number of flights (and power supply/battery capacity), so any cost equivalence is quickly overcome due to repeatability. The costs for acquiring UAS imagery are usually derived from the initial investment, the processing software, data storage, and associated (and ongoing) fieldwork expenses. However, after the initial investment, datasets can be delivered more often and at a higher resolution than by any other EO system.</p></oldvalue></delete><update digester="fnv" path="/3/1/3/12" radius="4" shortened="true"><fingerprint>1310d197;5039bbd1;858f8603;1310d194;027a9443;b6849fa8;662e3aec;9e1e725e;c7c66c3d</fingerprint><oldvalue>].</oldvalue><newvalue>]. While UAS systems cannot compete with satellite imagery in terms of spatial coverage, they provide unprecedented spatial and temporal resolutions unmatched by satellite alternatives. Furthermore, they do so at a fraction of the satellite acquisition cost if the area of interest has relatively small extent. For example, a newly tasked high-resolution natural color image (50 cm/pixel) from a satellite (e.g., GeoEye-1) can cost up to 3000 USD. On the other hand, the initial outlay to acquire a single UAS with a natural color camera can be less than 1000 USD (see </newvalue></update></delta>